Brian Novak

८ (620) 214-1850 | ☑ brian.novak.simulation@gmail.com | **۞** bnovak1 | **in** briannovak

Summary & Research Interests ____

I have applied molecular simulations to various systems including biomolecular systems, interaction of biomolecules with non-biological materials, rapid solidification of metals and alloys, growth of Cu on TiN, and bubble nucleation. My main research interests are:

- · Molecular and multiscale simulations of biomolecular systems
- Interaction of biomolecules with non-biological materials
- · Interfacial phenomena and phase change

Education _

University of Notre Dame

Ph.D., Chemical Engineering 2008/07

· Molecular simulation studies of heterogeneous bubble nucleation: Effects of surface chemistry and topology

Kansas State University

B.S., CHEMICAL ENGINEERING 2002/05

Additional Courses/Certifications

- Data Analyst with Python Track (2020/03)
- Python Programmer Track (2020/01)
- Medicinal Chemistry: The Molecular Basis of Drug Discovery (2019/11)
- Introduction to R (2019/10)
- Introduction to Time Series Analysis in Python (2019/10)
- Introduction to Programming with MATLAB (2015/12)

Skills _

Computer languages Python, MATLAB, Tcl, Mathematica, Fortran, R **MD related software** LAMMPS, GROMACS, NAMD, VMD, Ovito, Packmol

Other Linux, high performance computing

Research Experience

Louisiana State University

Molecular Simulation

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE 2007/11 - present

- Function and dynamics of the enzyme biotin carboxylase
 - Showed that the ATP binding domain of biotin carboxylase (BC) is most stable in a closed configuration for a monomer and most stable in an open configuration for a dimer which may explain the loss of activity for monomers relative to dimers
 - Showed that there is communication between monomers of a BC dimer when ATP is bound in one monomer, and that the most stable state in this case is one with both monomers closed, supporting other evidence suggesting that a reaction occurs in only one monomer at a time
- Sequencing DNA using times-of-flight of single nucleotides as they pass through nanochannels
 - Performed initial simulations in nanoslits. Slit walls were composed of a single type of atom in a disordered arrangement approximating polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA). Smooth and rough walls were considered.
 - Assisted graduate students with running simulations with slit walls composed of PMMA and self-assembled monolayers.
 - Extrapolated simulation results to estimate the slit length required to obtain a given error rate as a metric to compare different surfaces.
- Self-assembly of bile salts or cationic linear peptide analogs (LPAs) and their interaction with lipid bilayers
 - Assisted graduate student and advisor with running bile salt simulations
 - Showed that LPAs with hydrocarbon connectors longer than 7 carbons form small, stable micelles at high concentrations.
 - Showed that longer LPA hydrocarbon connectors lead to deeper penetration into lipid bilayers.
 - Observed the existence of a long-lived trans-bilayer configuration for LPAs with 11 carbon hydrocarbon connectors.
- Bulk and interfacial properties of liquid metals & alloys
- Parameterization of phase field models for rapid solidification of Ti & Ti-Ni alloys using molecular dynamics simulations
 - Performed simulations to obtain kinetic coefficients for Ti. Assisted graduate student with setup and analysis of other kinetic coefficient and interfacial free energy simulations.
 - Wrote python code to analyze solid-liquid interfacial properties including velocity, interfacial free energy, and concentration profiles.
- · Growth of Cu on TiN
 - Assisted graduate student with bulk and cluster simulations to show that Cu(100) grows on TiN(100) while Cu(110) grows on TiN(310)
 - Applied minima hopping global optimization to study initial Cu cluster growth
- Behavior of alpha-tocopherol (vitamin E) in lipid bilayers
 - Performed initial simulations. Assisted graduate student with further simulations.
 - Analyzed trajectory data to show that the higher flip-flop rate of tocopherol at higher concentrations in thinner bilayers such as DMPC is associated with tocopherol clusters that span the bilayer.
- Interaction of lignin oligomers with lipid bilayers or β-cyclodextrin or microwaves
 - Assisted graduate student with the design of the simulations.
 - Suggested a normalized deuterium order parameter averaged over several carbon atoms in the lipid tails for monitoring the lipid gelliquid crystalline phase transition.
- Interaction of poly(lactic-co-glycolic acid) (PLGA) nanoparticles with lipid bilayers
- Self-assembly of VECAR (vitamin E-carnosine) bolaamphiphiles
 - Assisted collaborators at Southeastern Louisiana University with simulation setup and analysis.
- Hybrid continuum/molecular dynamics simulations
 - Assisted graduate student with setup and analysis of simulations.
- Melting point estimation using unsupervised machine learning
 - Assisted collaborators in Physics Department with setup and analysis of simulations.

University of Notre Dame

Chemical Engineering

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2002/08 - 2007/09

- · Showed that 4.5 nm indentations cause a large increase in nucleation rate relative to a smooth surface, but 1.5 nm indentations have little effect
- Applied a thermodynamic model using Mathematica that explained the location of critical bubble nuclei near flat surfaces and extended this
 model to geometric surface defects

Kansas State University

Chemistry 1999/01 - 2001/01

Undergraduate Research Assistant

• Showed the effects of solute-gel interactions by measuring electrochemiluminescence intensities of Ru(bpy)₃²⁺ and diffusion coefficients of Co(bpy)₃²⁺ in silica gels and organically modified silica gels

Publications

- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B.; Tong, X.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of the Positioning and Dynamics of α-Tocopherol in Phospholipid Bilayers. Eur. Biophys. J. 2020, Submitted.
- Tong, X.; Novak, B.; Kavousi, S.; Moldovan, D. Single Nucleotides Moving Through Nanoslits Composed of Self-Assembled Monolayers via
 Equilibrium and Nonequilibrium Molecular Dynamics. J. Phys. Chem. B 2021, 125 (4), 1259–1270.
- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B. R.; Hoyt, J.; Moldovan, D. Interface Kinetics of Rapid Solidification of Binary Alloys by Atomistic Simulations: Application to Ti-Ni Alloys. Comput. Mater. Sci. 2020, 184, 109854.
- Tong, X.; Moradipour, M.; Novak, B.; Kamali, P.; Asare, S. O.; Knutson, B. L.; Rankin, S. E.; Lynn, B. C.; Moldovan, D. Experimental and Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of the Effects of Lignin Dimers on the Gel-to-Fluid Phase Transition in DPPC Bilayers. J. Phys. Chem. B 2019, 123 (39), 8247–8260.
- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B. R.; Baskes, M. I.; Zaeem, M. A.; Moldovan, D. Modified Embedded-Atom Method Potential for High-Temperature Crystal-Melt Properties of Ti–Ni Alloys and Its Application to Phase Field Simulation of Solidification. *Modelling Simul. Mater. Sci. Eng.* 2019, 28 (1), 015006.
- Muley, P. D.; Mobley, J. K.; Tong, X.; Novak, B.; Stevens, J.; Moldovan, D.; Shi, J.; Boldor, D. Rapid Microwave-Assisted Biomass Delignification and Lignin Depolymerization in Deep Eutectic Solvents. *Energy Convers. Manag.* 2019, 196, 1080–1088.
- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B. R.; Zaeem, M. A.; Moldovan, D. Combined Molecular Dynamics and Phase Field Simulation Investigations of Crystal-Melt Interfacial Properties and Dendritic Solidification of Highly Undercooled Titanium. Comput. Mater. Sci. 2019, 163, 218–229.
- Walker, N.; Tam, K.-M.; Novak, B.; Jarrell, M. Identifying Structural Changes with Unsupervised Machine Learning Methods. Phys. Rev. E 2018, 98 (5), 053305.
- Kim, H.-Y.; Novak, B. R.; Shrestha, B.; Lee, S. E.; Moldovan, D. The Role of the Asymmetric Bolaamphiphilic Character of VECAR on the Kinetic
 and Structural Aspects of Its Self-Assembly: A Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study. Colloids Surf. Physicochem. Eng. Asp. 2017, 523, 9–18.
- Xia, K.; Novak, B. R.; Weerakoon-Ratnayake, K. M.; Soper, S. A.; Nikitopoulos, D. E.; Moldovan, D. Electrophoretic Transport of Single DNA Nucleotides Through Nanoslits: A Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study. *J. Phys. Chem. B* 2015, 119 (35), 11443–11458.
- Sabliov, C. M.; Moldovan, D.; Novak, B.; Borel, T.; Whaley, M. Cellular Fate of Delivery Systems and Entrapped Bioactives. In Nanotechnology and Functional Foods: Effective Delivery of Bioactive Ingredients; Sabliov, C. M., Chen, H., Yada, R., Eds.; Wiley-Blackwell, 2015; pp 35–51.
- Novak, B. R.; Moldovan, D.; Nikitopoulos, D. E.; Soper, S. A. Distinguishing Single DNA Nucleotides Based on Their Times of Flight through Nanoslits: A Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study. J. Phys. Chem. B 2013, 117 (12), 3271–3279.
- Lin, J.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of the Effect of DMSO on Structural and Permeation Properties of DMPC Lipid Bilayers. J. Phys. Chem. B 2012, 116, 1299–1308.
- Novak, B. R.; Moldovan, D.; Waldrop, G. L.; de Queiroz, M. S. Behavior of the ATP Grasp Domain of Biotin Carboxylase Monomers and Dimers Studied Using Molecular Dynamics Simulations. Proteins: Struct. Funct. Bioinform. 2011, 79, 622–632.
- Novak, B. R.; Moldovan, D.; Waldrop, G. L.; de Queiroz, M. S.. Umbrella Sampling Simulations of Biotin Carboxylase: Is a Structure with an Open ATP Grasp Domain Stable in Solution? J. Phys. Chem. B 2009, 113 (30), 10097–10103.
- Novak, B. R.; Maginn, E. J.; McCready, M. J. An Atomistic Simulation Study of the Role of Asperities and Indentations on Heterogeneous Bubble Nucleation. J. Heat Trans.-T. ASME 2008, 130.
- Novak, B. R.; Maginn, E. J.; McCready, M. J. Comparison of Heterogeneous and Homogeneous Bubble Nucleation Using Molecular Simulations. *Phys. Rev. B* 2007, 75.
- Collinson, M. M.; Novak, B. Diffusion and Reactivity of Ruthenium (II) Tris(Bipyridine) and Cobalt (II) Tris(Bipyridine) in Organically Modified Silicates. J. Sol-Gel Sci. Technol. 2002, 23, 215–220.
- Collinson, M. M.; Novak, B.; Martin, S. A.; Taussig, J. S. Electrochemiluminescence of Ruthenium(II) Tris(Bipyridine) Encapsulated in Sol–Gel
 Glasses. Anal. Chem. 2000, 72 (13), 2914–2918.

Presentations

Oral - Invited

• Molecular Dynamics Simulations of Biological Systems: Enzyme Conformational Change and Small Molecule (DNA) Sequencing, Southeastern LA Univ. Chemistry & Physics Seminar (2010). In Southeastern LA Univ. Chemistry & Physics Seminar; 2010.

Oral - Conference

- Tong, X.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Simulation of Single Nucleotides Moving through Nanoslits Composed of Self-Assembled Monolayers Terminated with Various Chemical Groups. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2018.
- Novak, B.; Raush, J.; Zhang, X.; Moldovan, D.; Meng, W.; Guo, S. Properties of Liquid Ti Alloys from Electrostatic Levitation Experiments and Simulation. In APS March Meeting; 2017.
- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Self-Assembly of Linear Peptide Analogs and Their Interaction with Lipid Bilayers Using MD Simulations. In 89th ACS Colloid & Surface Science Symposium; 2015.
- Novak, B. R.; Lin, J.; Moldovan, D. MD Simulations of Cationic Linear Peptide Analogs: Self-Assembly and Interaction with DPPC and DPPC/DPPS Lipid Bilayers. In ACS Fall National Meeting; 2014.
- Novak, B. R.; Lin, J.; Moldovan, D. Interaction of Cationic Linear Peptide Analogs with Negatively Charged Lipid Bilayers Studied with Molecular Dynamics Simulations. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2013.
- Novak, B.; Astete, C.; Sabliov, C.; Moldovan, D. Interaction of PLGA nanoparticles with a DMPC bilayer studied using molecular dynamics simulations. In APS March Meeting; 2012.
- Novak, B.; Xia, K.; Moldovan, D.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Soper, S. **Simulations of Single DNA Nucleotide Transport Through Nanoslits**. In *APS March Meeting*; 2011.
- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Waldrop, G. L.; de Queiroz, M. S. Opening/Closing Dynamics and Subunit Communication in Biotin Carboxylase.
 In Southwest & Southeastern Regional Meeting of the ACS; 2010.
- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Soper, S. Molecular Dynamics Simulations of the Transport of Single DNA Nucleotides Through Nanochannels. In APS March Meeting; 2010.
- Novak, B.; Maginn, E. J.; McCready, M. J. Applying a Thermodynamic Model to Predict the Size of Surface Indentations That Affect Bubble Nucleation. In AIChE Annual Meeting; 2007.
- Novak, B.; Maginn, E. J.; McCready, M. J. Molecular Dynamics Investigation of Bubble Nucleation at a Solid Surface. In Midwest Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics Conference; 2006.
- Novak, B.; Maginn, E. J.; McCready, M. J. Effects of Geometric Defects on Superheated Heterogeneous Bubble Nucleation: A Molecular Dynamics Study. In AIChE Annual Meeting; 2006.
- Novak, B.; Maginn, E. J.; McCready, M. J. Superheated Homogeneous and Heterogeneous Bubble Nucleation Rates Using NPT and NP_{zz}T Molecular Dynamics: Effects of Surface Interactions. In AIChE Annual Meeting; 2005.

Poster - Conference

- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Waldrop, G.; de Queiroz, M. Insights into the Opening and Closing Dynamics of Biotin Carboxylase. In APS March Meeting; 2010.
- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Waldrop, G.; de Queiroz, M. Opening and Closing of Biotin Carboxylase: Free Energies and Mean First Passage Times. In *Mardi Gras Conference*; 2010.
- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Soper, S. Molecular Dynamics Simulations for Calculation of Times of Flight of Single DNA Nucleotides Driven through Nanochannels. In *Mardi Gras Conference*; 2010.
- Novak, B.; Lin, J.; Moldovan, D.; Jha, S.; Soper, S.; Nikitopoulos, D. MD Simulations of DNA Mononucleotide Transport through Nanochannels. In 21st EPSCoR National Conference; 2009.
- Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Waldrop, G.; de Queiroz, M. **Umbrella Sampling Simulations of the Closure of Biotin Carboxylase**. In *International Conference on Multiscale Materials Modeling*; 2008.

Author only

- Tong, X.; Maradipour, M.; Novak, B.; Knutson, B.; Rankin, S.; Lynn, B.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of the Effect of Lignin Dimers on the Gel to Liquid-Crystalline Transition Temperature in DPPC Bilayers. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2019.
- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Phase Field Modeling of Rapid Solidification of Ti-Ni Alloy Parameterized Using Interfacial Properties Calculated from Atomistic Simulations. In MRS Fall Meeting; 2019.
- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Combined Molecular Dynamics and Phase Field Simulation Study of Directional Solidification of NiTi Alloy. In TMS Annual Meeting & Exhibition; 2019.
- Kavousi, S.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. **Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of Alpha-Tocopherol Interaction with Lipid Bilayers**. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2018.
- Walker, N.; Novak, B.; Tam, K. M.; Moldovan, D.; Jarrell, M. **Ab Initio Calculations of Transport in Titanium and Aluminum Mixtures**. In *APS March Meeting*; 2017.
- Tam, K. M.; Novak, B.; Walker, N.; Moldovan, D.; Jarrell, M. Finite Size Scaling of the First Order Transition of Molecular Systems. In APS March Meeting; 2017.
- Raush, J.; Novak, B.; Zhang, X.; Moldovan, D.; Meng, W.; Guo, S. Measurement and Calculation of Liquid Ti Alloy Properties with Application to 3D Printing. In 4th World Congress on Integrated Computational Materials Engineering; 2017.
- Shrestha, B.; Kim, H.-Y.; Lee, S.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Self-Assemblies of Novel Molecules, VECAR. In APS March Meeting; 2015.
- Novak, B.; Lin, J.; Moldovan, D. Investigation of Linear Peptide Analogs Self-Assembly and Interaction with DPPC and DPPC/DPPS Lipid Bilayers: A Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study. In The Central and Eastern European Conference on Health and the Environment; 2014.
- Xia, K.; Lin, J.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Electrically Driven Single DNA Nucleotides through Nanoslits. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2013.
- Lin, J.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of Bile Salt Aggregation and Interaction with Vitamin E. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2013.
- Xia, K.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Soper, S. MD Simulation Study of the Effect of Electric Field on the Dynamics of DNA Nucleotides in Hydrophobic Nanoslits. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2012.
- Novak, B.; Xia, K.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Soper, S.; Moldovan, D. Atomistic Simulation Study of Single DNA Nucleotide Transport through Nanoslits. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2012.
- Novak, B.; Lin, J.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Adsorption and Positioning of Vitamin E in DMPC Lipid Bilayers: Implication for Their Antioxidant Inhibition. In Colloids and Nanomedicine; 2012.
- Lin, J.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Bile Salts Micelle Self-Assembly in Aqueous Solutions. In ACS Spring National Meeting; 2012.
- Moldovan, D.; Alapati, R.; Novak, B.; Devireddy, R. Molecular Dynamics Simulation Study of Structural Changes and Pore Formation in Phospholipid Bilayers in the Presence of Dimethylsulfoxide. In APS March Meeting; 2010.
- Novak, B.; Xia, K.; Moldovan, D.; Nikitopoulos, D.; Soper, S. Molecular Dynamics Simulations of the Movement of Single DNA Nucleotides through Nanoslits. In Southwest & Southeastern Regional Meeting of the ACS; 2010.
- Lao, J.; Lin, J.; Xia, K.; Sabliov, C.; Moldovan, D. Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Self-Assembly of Span80 into Micelles and Their Interaction with Vitamin E. In Mardi Gras Conference; 2010.
- Chantiwas, R.; Hupert, M.; Lopez, J.; Datta, P.; Gottert, J.; Novak, B.; Moldovan, D.; Jha, S.; Park, S.; Murphy, M.; et al. Transport of Single Molecules through Nanochannels: A Novel Approach to DNA Sequencing. In International Conference on Miniaturized Systems for Chemistry and Life Sciences; 2009.

Peer Reviewing _____

- Improved kinetic description of fast relaxation of cylindrical micelles, Physica A, 2018-10-11
- Shuffled lipidation pattern and degree of lipidation determines the membrane interaction behavior of a linear cationic membrane-active peptide, Mol. Pharm., 2018-04-29
- Rapid Transport of Deformation-Tuned Nanoparticles across Biological Hydrogels and Cellular Barriers, Nat. Commun., 2017-12-05

Leadership & Teaching Experience _____

Louisiana State University

Baton Rouge, LA

MENTOR

• 7 graduate students

• 10 undergraduate students

2007/11 - present

Louisiana State University

MATLAB Course Instructor

2015/Fall

Baton Rouge, LA

University of Notre Dame

Chemical Engineering

TEACHING ASSISTANT

2002/08 - 2004/05

- Chemical Engineering Laboratory II (Fall 2002) Supervised 3 experiments
- Chemical Engineering Laboratory I (Spring 2003) Supervised 2 experiments
- Introduction to Chemical Engineering (Fall 2003) Graded homework and tests
- Global Climate Change (Spring 2004) Homework solutions and grading